so who has a hand up at the back here
and one here great so that's we're gonna
hear a couple let's take three questions
as a whole and then we're kind of person
to you to field and maybe you just say
who you are when you ask the question
also thank you I'm Steve Cunningham I'm
a visitor to Scotland and Finn horn from
Alaska yeah I would just like to get the
panel's thoughts on two different things
the Baha'i faith and Jordan Peterson if
they have any number Baha'i faith the
bahá'í faith and Jordan and Jordan
Peterson you want to explain who Jordan
Peterson is the people who died Jordan
Peterson is a former University of
Toronto professor clinical psychologist
it's working with a lot of young people
these days and he's recently written a
book called twelve rules for life to
give young people meaning in the
seemingly hopeless situation they find
themselves in and the Baha'i faith
claims to be a universal religion
uniting all the former religions ok
great let's hold that question we'll
take one of the back here
you could introduce yourself and say
yeah my name's John Lautner my my
question really is a number but a number
of the speakers emphasized the
significance of paradox in their
understanding and it seems to me that
we're living in an age in the mainstream
where paradoxes are increasingly being
vilified and trying to escape from from
paradox and I wondered what the view of
the panel was well they could elaborate
more on the importance of paradox as a
way of emerging from this very very
narrow restricted way of living that we
are in at the moment great thank you
let's maybe start with those two so a
question about the nature of paradox and
also about Jordan Peterson and the
Baha'i faith who would like to kick off
I can't say much about Jordan Peterson I
don't know about him I have met a few
boys and they all were wonderful people
but that's really all I can say about
that but about the paradox if we take it
to what we learned about this great
thought that is one big hole that needs
to we need the separation in order to
have a perspective on it but we at the
same time that hole we waves in that
ocean that invites us into understanding
that this belief that if I hold one view
and somebody else holds the seemingly
exclusive other view then one of us
needs to be wrong but that's a mistake
if what we really need is lots of
different angles on reality and
sometimes they seem to be mutually
exclusive but actually when when we work
with that polarity then we enter into a
deeper understanding
of our participation and co-creation of
this whole so I think putting paradoxes
away or saying oh that well that doesn't
make any sense because it's mutually
exclusive and is a way of keeping us in
the story of separation and stopping us
from experiencing interbeing and
co-creation thanks Daniel I'd like to
add to that if I may I'm afraid I don't
know Jordans work either and a limited
perspective the bajas I guess where I'm
having a sense of is that the whole
universe exists and evolves as a central
universe so love this unity expressed in
diversity so our whole experience of
differentiation and diversity is
innately embedded in the evolutionary
impulse of the universe which also
speaks to your point on on the
appearance of paradox but also it
suggests again I think what William was
saying is that as we as we're able to
feel free as we're able to feel
authentic as we're able to to literally
step into our conscious co-create
ivities
there are many roads at the same
mountain you know in terms of spiritual
practice in terms of religious cultural
perspectives there are many roads at the
same mountain and I think to say there
is one religion however apparently
generic it is suggests that there is
still that path it may be very broad my
sense is that our emergence our
conscious evolutionary potential enables
us to welcome and celebrate that
diversity and also find ways perhaps of
reconciling apparent paradox I talk
about you know duality to polarity to
relativity so that we are aware of being
in relationship with all life in the
sense that if period can appear very
different but ultimately it is part of
that ultimate wholeness but expressed in
amazing abundant diverse
and differentiation when I teach my
grade 12 economics block I often think
of subtitling it welcome to paradox I
think it's a great question and I can
think of any in any given moment how I'm
experiencing it I'm very much aware of
the IPCC findings released this week and
I flew to Scotland in the same week so
if that's not a paradox I don't know
what is and I look at actually this rug
here is a great example we could each
take points on this rug and be kind of
across from each other in seeming
polarity and yet we do have the
possibility of reconstructing the whole
picture out of that and I it always
seems to me that that's just about the
definition of what it means to be human
how do we hold that Center and and
redefine the whole I'll just say
something obvious just being incarnate
is a paradox isn't it creech creatures
with cosmic consciousness strung out
between biological instincts and
developmental soul inspired expansion
yeah
that paradox that it requires some
maturity to be at ease with it and
sometimes I see that maturity and
children who are just at ease with it
and yeah yeah thank you let's see if
there's other questions that want to
emerge at the back here maybe there's
two at the back oh there's one over here
so I can't see you a little bit in the
dark but there's somebody here and
somebody a woman here in the row before
the back is what here was a microphone
this one there with a microphone also a
Roger in there from the crowd but let's
hear from you first I'd like to thank
everyone for your talks and I strongly
resonate with a lot of what was said I
just wanted to say that after the IPCC
report a after already having lost a lot
of help I read that the Australian
Government had refused to stop coal
mining and so I just wonder how all of
the approaches that you've mentioned can
filter into politics because I feel like
the moment whilst changes are happening
in the political spectrum it doesn't
seem to be the case so much and it still
dominates a lot of of how the world
works so I would like to hear your
thoughts on that thank you so one
question about politics Roger you want
to add we're just taking a couple
together
yeah in a way it's the same same kind of
theme after the announcement of the
latest UN climate change panel the BBC
ran an interesting program called the
moral maze and the key question that
they were looking at was is it moral is
it more moral to curtail the welfare of
people who are already alive and are
already struggling predominantly in
developing world depended upon cheap
electricity for any sense of progress is
it more moral to look
after their knees than it is to consider
the welfare of people who are not even
yet born 2050 on down the road in a
planet which may be increasing it will
be probably increasingly uninhabitable
and you know i-i-i I don't know the
answer that question I want you or you
do okay so a question about how we might
take some of this awareness here into
the political arena and a question about
the morality of caring for future
generations in a way that you frame it
at the expense of people who are
currently alive particularly in the
global south so who would like to
respond to that a couple of thoughts on
that as a healer I was invited after the
u.s. election in November 2016 to
contribute from Havana Festo guided by
over lászló called beyond fear and rage
and I wrote a piece called the
flickering of hope and what I wrote in
there was that when complex systems are
ready to change when they're at the
point of breakdown potentially then what
you find on those underlying attractors
are showed earlier is you get the limits
of the behavior of a system beginning to
just break down but you also get the
potential izing of a higher level of
coherence a possibility also forming and
what you have is what's called a
bifurcation point but in that
bifurcation point which can be break
down and/or break through you have
something called flickering where there
is a flickering between the old system
that is essentially falling apart and
the potent izing of the the higher level
of coherence and they flicker between
the two and if there is sufficient if
you like consciousness it's a sufficient
essence to that higher level coherence
the system streams through to that and
that is essentially as we're finding in
informational terms as well which of
course is
consciousness expressing itself as
information emergence is biological
emergence so it seems to me that as a
collective psyche as we are all
interconnected there are areas of our
collective psyche that has that still
embodies trauma from all the appearance
of separation that we've been through
for so long and that's energizing as it
were the the current your unsustainable
situation but there's also higher level
coherence as I go around the world I'm
seeing incredible incredible movements
that are gaining momentum and
accelerating such as what you're doing
in the Hudson what Williams been doing
what you've been doing Daniel but across
the world as well as the breakdown and I
think we're in this time of flickering
and it's almost as though were in the
birth canal of conscious evolution and
when we're in the birth canal I'm not a
mum but my mum used to help the local
Midwife and her advice was always
breathe and push so there has the sense
I have and I think that's the sense on
the political side as well cuz we're
seeing that and it's on the sense that
you're talking about Roger as well thank
you I've got two thoughts one is always
always always keep on campaigning keep
on campaigning keep on campaigning yet
simultaneously step back and celebrate
the level of debate that's going on
because the apparent disaster is not
going on silently there are huge
arguments there are huge debates they're
huge pushes to get appropriate
legislation in battles will be lost
apparently Wars occasionally will be
lost but keep on campaigning and keep
your eye on the fact that it's a hot
subject and that's to be celebrated
nobody is going through all this
apathetically and that for me is a
huge indication that humanity as a whole
is waking up to its self responsibility
in relation to its environment so keep
on campaigning but don't get depressed
by the bad news because you get
depressed by the bad news you're just
going to shovel more shit on to it you
know the vibe doesn't work keep
campaigning and hang out with people
who've got a an eye on the long picture
and the fact that it it's tough now but
we'll be ok I I have to check in with
myself because that's really like locus
of control that I have in how am I
dealing with these questions which are
large and challenging and it's quite
easy to become cynical in the political
sphere especially in the country that
I'm from and I feel that in this process
of becoming human which I think we're
still on that journey where we need to
connect to our deepest source of who we
are and my dear friend Otto Sharma would
say we need to approach that with an
open mind open heart and open will and
it's our own voices of judgment our own
voices of cynicism and our own voices of
fear that will prevent us from doing
that so this is what I have to do I know
the work that I have to do I just want
to equal this internal locus of control
and it's one of the key principles of
regenerative development is that it
starts within and to be facing the
current political situation in a lot of
countries what's going on in Brazil as
well at the moment is very concerning I
think
when we need to keep campaigning we need
to keep calling political leaders out
for being in bed with money but I think
that there's something powerful about
this by a regional approach to bring
politics back to the scale where people
have an interaction at the local and by
regional level where I as we're moving
into a regenerative like if we get it
right in this century will be remembered
as the century of regeneration then I
also think we will be a long way towards
the abolishment of new nation states I
don't think that the nation-state is fit
for the 22nd century we it's part of
that era of Empires it's defining us
against other my one of my favorite
musicians Michael Franti says do you
love just one nation and the whole world
will will divide if we bring it back
down to the level of by regionalism we
can see how our actions and this is
beginning to answer Rodgers question I
don't think that there's a dynamic of
tension between present generations and
future generations the path of
regenerative development is a path where
we are moving towards healing the
ecosystems which creates jobs which
creates every regionalization of
production and consumption towards
biomaterials and that actually improves
the conditions of this generation and in
doing so we'll set the scene for
improving the conditions of future
generations thank you I think we'll draw
our proceedings to a close now to honor
our time commitments and also your
energy and also your energy and I want
to do that with a with many thank yous
actually first of all huge thank you to
four fantastic speakers and a great
panel today
Martin and William thank you so much
it's been a it's been a fantastic
fantastic launching of interim talks
stay tuned I'm sure there will be more
so and also a huge thank you to John
Clausen for an enormous amount of work
to get it together and to Thomas George
also for supporting that many thanks to
all of you thanks to our sponsors the
Fenton foundation a solar Phoenix
cafe and shop and the hygeia foundation
for enabling this to happen
I think round of applause definitely for
our sponsors and to our all our
technical folks the people who are
helping the livestream to happen we've
got a great team of people filming this
we've had over 260 people able to watch
and absorb and benefit from this through
the efforts of our technicians people of
the soundest the lighting folk let's
also appreciate them so many thanks to
all of you
and let's also close with a moment of
quiet and stillness as we start it and
when to invite you to close your eyes if
you wish and just create however you do
it a little inner spaciousness and take
a moment to notice how you are in your
body your heart your mind your spirit
what has moved and touched you this
evening waters may be concerned or
irritated you this evening just being
present to all of your experience and
welcoming it all
noticing also what conversations or
movements you want to continue or deepen
and let's just have a moment of
gratitude for all that has transpired
this evening our inner experience our
outer experience all the beings that
have supported they're seen and unseen
and let's dedicate this time to the good
of all beings to the unfolding of the
highest and the best
and let's give thanks that it is so
Thank You beloved thank you beloved's
thank you for coming and God blessed and
go well and may we just have a final
round of applause for Robyn who's an
amazing job this evening
[Applause]